<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="defining-flows">
	<title>Defining Flows</title>
	<sect1 id="introduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			This chapter begins the Users Section of this guide.
			It shows how to implement flows using the flow definition language.
			By the end of this chapter, you should have a good understanding of language constructs and capable of authoring a flow definition.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="flow-overview">
		<title>What is a Flow?</title>
		<para>
			A flow encapsulates a reusable sequence of steps that can execute in different contexts.
			Below is a <ulink url="http://www.jjg.net/ia/visvocab/">Garrett Information Architecture</ulink> diagram illustrating a reference to a flow that encapsulates the steps of a hotel booking process:
		</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject role="fo">
				<imagedata fileref="images/hotels-site.png" format="PNG" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<imageobject role="html">
				<imagedata fileref="images/hotels-site.png" format="PNG" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<caption>
				<para>A BookHotel Flow Definition</para>
			</caption>
		</mediaobject>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="flow-makeup">
		<title>What is the makeup of a typical Flow?</title>
		<para>
			In Spring Web Flow, a flow consists of a series of steps called "states".
			Entering a state typically results in a page being displayed to the user.
			On the page, user events occur that are handled by that state.
			These events can trigger transitions to other states which result in page navigations.
		</para>
		<para>
			The example below shows the structure of the book hotel flow referenced in the previous diagram:
		</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject role="fo">
				<imagedata fileref="images/hotels-site-bookhotel-flow.png" format="PNG" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<imageobject role="html">
				<imagedata fileref="images/hotels-site-bookhotel-flow.png" format="PNG" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<caption>
				<para>Hotels Site Diagram that references a "Book Hotel" flow</para>
			</caption>
		</mediaobject>		
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="flow-definition">
		<title>How are Flows authored?</title>
		<para>
			Flows are authored by web application developers using a XML-based flow definition language.
			The next steps of this guide will walk you through the elements of this language.
		</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>